The Dark Knight fights to save Gotham city from its deadliest enemy.
Batman: Mask of the Phantasm is a action, animation,
crime film directed by Bruce Timm.
Andrea Beaumont leaves her father to return to Gotham,
rekindling an old romance with Bruce Wayne.
At the same time, a mysterious figure begins to hunt down Gotham's
criminals, wrongly implicating Batman in the murders.
Now on the run from the law, Batman must find and stop the culprit,
while also navigating his relationship with Andrea.
Bruce Wayne / Batman (voice), played by Kevin Conroy.
Andrea Beaumont / Chimera (voice), played by Dana Delany.
Arthur Reeves (voice), played by Hart Bochner.
Phantasm / Carl Beaumont (voice), played by Stacy Keach.
The Joker (voice), played by Mark Hamill.
Salvatore Valestra (voice), played by Abe Vigoda.
Batman: Mask of the Phantasm is a 1993 American animated
superhero film featuring the DC Comics character Batman.
It was directed by Eric Radomski and Bruce Timm, and written by Alan
Burnett, Paul Dini, Martin Pasko, and Michael Reaves.
The film is based on Batman: The Animated Series (1992–1995), and is the first film of
the DC Animated Universe and the only one to receive a theatrical release.
Kevin Conroy, Mark Hamill, Efrem Zimbalist Jr., Bob Hastings and Robert Costanzo reprise their voice roles from Batman:
The Animated Series, joined by Dana Delany, Hart Bochner, Stacy Keach, Abe Vigoda, Dick Miller and John P.
Produced between the first and second seasons of the series, the film follows Batman as he reconciles with a former lover, Andrea
Beaumont, and faces a mysterious vigilante, the titular Phantasm, who is murdering Gotham City's crime bosses.
The plot partly mirrors Mike W.
Barr's "Batman: Year Two" comic book story arc, with the Reaper from it loosely inspiring the Phantasm character made for the film, while also
borrowing elements from the "Batman: Year One" arc, recounting how Bruce Wayne became Batman and his first attempts to fight crime.
Originally planned for a direct-to-video release, Warner Bros.
ultimately gave Mask of the Phantasm a theatrical release, condensing
its production into a strenuous eight-month schedule.
The film was the first theatrical feature film produced by Warner Bros.
Animation, and was released through the studio's Family Entertainment label on December 25, 1993, to generally
positive reviews from critics, who praised the stylized animation, voice performances, story, and music.
Due to the decision to release it in theaters on short notice,
Mask of the Phantasm failed at the box office.
After its release on home media, it became financially successful.
Until the limited release of Batman: The Killing Joke in 2016, Mask of the Phantasm was the only animated Batman film to be given a
theatrical release, as well as the only one to receive a full theatrical release until The Lego Batman Movie in 2017.
The film explores themes of secret identity, superhero,
cartoon, based on comic, organized crime.
The tone is dark and emotional and mind_bending.